ILGWU Pennsylvania Records 5780/204
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
ILGWU Pennsylvania Records
1951-1999
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union (ILGWU)
5780/204
2.94 cubic feet
2.9 linear ft.
Records (documents).
Contains files on several local unions, district councils, and district departments in Pennsylvania. Especially well-documented are the organizing efforts of Northeastern Pennsylvania's Stakeholder Alliance and the 1994 strike of Leslie Fay in Wilkes-Barre, Pennsylvania. Records relating to the ILGWU chorus may be found in the files on local union 295 and the Wyoming Valley District. Also contains meeting minutes of local union 295, local 249 and 327, and the Hazleton District Council.
6766087
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, May 17, 2011
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, April 16, 2019
Biographical / Historical
The International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union was once one of the largest labor unions in the United States founded in 1900 by local union delegates representing about 2,000 members in cities in the northeastern United States. It was one of the first U.S. Unions to have a membership consisting of mostly females, and it played a key role in the labor history of the 1920s and 1930s. The union is generally referred to as the "ILGWU" or the "ILG". The ILGWU grew in geographical scope, membership size, and political influence to become one of the most powerful forces in American organized labor by mid-century. Representing workers in the women's garment industry, the ILGWU worked to improve working and living conditions of its members through collective bargaining agreements, training programs, health care facilities, cooperative housing, educational opportunities, and other efforts. The ILGWU merged with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union in 1995 to form the Union of Needle trades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE). UNITE merged with the Hotel Employees and Restaurant Employees Union (HERE) in 2004 to create a new union known as UNITE HERE. The two unions that formed UNITE in 1995 represented only 250,000 workers between them, down from the ILGWU's peak membership of 450,000 in 1969.
Biographical / Historical
The ILGWU's extensive work to organize garment workers in Pennsylvania (outside of Philadelphia) resulted in the formation of several district councils throughout the state and especially in central Pennsylvania.
Beginning in 1957 as the Central and Western Pennsylvania District, the Central Pennsylvania District was an affiliate within the ILGWU's Northeast Region. With the affiliate into two and renamed the Central Pennsylvania District and the Western Pennsylvania District by 1962, Central Pennsylvania District Council included four local unions (108, 170, 196, and 197) until 1987. From 1988 until the ILGWU's merger with ACTWU in 1995, the affiliate was reorganized as the Central and Western Pennsylvania and Reading District Council. During this period, the council included as many as eight local unions (98, 108, 170, 196, 197, 217, 424, and 445).
Throughout its existence, the Central Pennsylvania District Council worked closely with other affiliates in the Northeast Department, including local unions in Easton, Hazleton, Reading, Scranton, Shamokin, Sunbury, Pottstown, and Pottsville. By the 1960s, the ILGWU had established district councils in Scranton and Easton. In the 1970s, additional local unions were organized into the Shamokin-Sunbury District Council (185, 306), Hazleton District Council (225, 575), and the Wyoming Valley District Council (249, 327).
With the decline of manufacturing in the region in the 1980s and 1990s, these affiliates began to merge. The year 1986 saw the creation of the Shamokin-Sunbury-Pottsville District Council, and in 1990, the Scranton District Council was included in this affiliate. After 1988, the Hazleton and Wyoming Valley District merged.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of records and files for the locals, districts, and departments within Pennsylvania. There is executive board material for the various locals including rosters and tally sheets, as well as meeting minutes. Also available is general local material such as correspondence, notes and memos, newsletters and publications, and finances. Another aspect of the collection illustrates the activities of the locals with information on events and dinners, charity balls, anniversary dinners, dances, plays and revues that were put on by drama departments, and material from the ILGWU chorus from Local 295 and the Wyoming Valley District.
There are clippings and articles of local interest. Well documented is the Leslie Fay Company, a large employer and manufacturer in the Wilkes-Barre area. Included are sewing manuals for pattern pieces, and detailed instructions for linings, facings, piping, zippers, joining pieces, adding darts, pleats, gussets, and piece rates. Also available and of importance is all the correspondence, meeting memos and clippings from the 1990s when the Leslie Fay Company decided to move operations out of the country, effecting 2,000 jobs, the 1994 strike, and the subsequent union campaign to get the company to stay.
Another component of the collection is the files of Lois Hartel, district manager of the Hazleton-Wyoming District. Aside from correspondence and union business, there are oversize posters of voting machine instructions for the primary on April 10, 1984, of which Lois Hartel was a candidate for delegate for the Democratic National Convention from the 11th Congressional District.
Over time, many of the locals merged to form districts, and ones that are represented in the collection include: Local 249 Wilkes-Barre; Local 295 Pittston; Local 327 Nanticoke; Wyoming Valley District-249, 295 &327; Central Pennsylvania District 108; Local 196; Local 170; Easton District; Hazleton District (225 Hazleton, PA and 575 Berwick, PA); Local 351; the Northeast, Western Pennsylvania and Ohio Department; Shamokin-Sunbury District; Reading-Pottstown District; Scranton-Shamokin-Sunbury-Pottsville District; Wilkes-Barre Locals 327-295-249.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5780: ILGWU records
Textile industry -- Pennsylvania.; Textile workers -- Labor unions -- Pennsylvania.; Clothing workers -- Labor unions -- Pennsylvania.; Clothing trade -- Labor unions -- Pennsylvania.; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union; Union of Needletrades, Industrial, and Textile Employees; UNITE HERE (Organization); Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union; Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union. Research Department
6766087
- Local 249/327 Executive Board Minutes, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Local 295, 25th Anniversary, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Local 295, Executive Committee Meeting Minutes, 1979-1988 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Local 295, list of individual jobbers (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Scope and Contents
  no date
- Local 295, 1958-1972 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Local 295, 1958-1970 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Local 295, 1958-1970 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Central Pennsylvania, 1979-1983 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Easton District, 1957-1979 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Hazelton District Council Minutes, 1983-1988 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Hazleton-Wyoming Valley District, 1983-1995 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Northeast Department, 1959-1992 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- NE, Western Pennsylvania, and Ohio Department, 1982-1987 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Reading-Pottstown District, 1962-1980 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Shamokin-Sunbury District, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Scranton District, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Scranton/Shamokin/Sunbury/Pottsville District Council, 1990-1995 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Wyoming Valley District, 1960-1980 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Wilkes Barre Locals 327-295-249 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Bianco, Sam, 1961-1975 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Hartel, Lois petition to be 1984 delegate to Democratic National Convention (DNC) (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Miller, Lois (Hartel), 1978-1989 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Hartel, Lois, 1970-1988 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Hartel, Lois, breakdowns, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Activities, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Bowl for Kids' Sake, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Desert Storm Show, August 29, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Exeter Fashions, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Fight for the Living (Workers Memorial Day), April 28, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Gable, Bill retirement party, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Governor's Study Commission on the Apparel Industry, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Health and Safety Department, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Leslie Fay, 1969-1990 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Leslie Fay, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Leslie Fay, 1982-1988 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Leslie Fay Stakeholder Alliance Cards, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Leslie Fay, correspondence, meeting materials, miscellaneous, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Leslie Fay, correspondence, meeting materials, miscellaneous, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Leslie Fay, correspondence, meeting materials, miscellaneous, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Leslie Fay, clippings, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Miscellany, 1968-1988 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Miscellany, 1964-1995 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Pennsylvania, 1965-1976 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Pennsylvania, American Federation of Labor-Congress of Industrial Organizations (AFL-CIO), 1963-1966 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Pennsylvania, American Federation of Labor-Congress of Industrial Organizations (AFL-CIO), 1963-1966 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Political, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Margaret, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  Press?
- 75th Anniversary, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Sheet music (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Textile and Apparel Teachers Association of Pennsylvania, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Tri-District Health Center, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Unity House, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Brief History of the ILGWU by Gewen, Barry (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Manual on Internal Organizing, Organizing Department, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- An Outline of Grievance Procedures in the Garment Industry, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- The Needle's Eye, Locals 234 and 243, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Needlepoint, Wilkes-Barre, Pittston, Nanticoke District Council, 1957-1963 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Northeast News, 1971-1973 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  publication of the Northeast Department
- Northeastern News, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  Scranton District Council
- Pennsylvania Organizer, 1956-1957 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  Organization Department
- "piece-rates, payroll, and people", 1977 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Pittston Guide, 1963-1977 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  Local 295
- A Policy Guide on Enforcing the Union Agreement, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  Northeast Department
- The Torch, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  Reading-Pottstown District
- Union Worker, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  Northeast and Western Pennsylvania Department
- Union Worker, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  Local 351
- Unity News, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  Locals185 and 306
- Education Department publications, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Political Department, 1964-1977 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Supplementary Unemployment and Severance Benefits, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Union Label Department Publications, 1959-1966 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Miscellaneous printed materials (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Miscellaneous printed materials (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Clippings, 1970-1979 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Clippings, 1980-1989 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Clippings, 1990-1999 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- ACTWU/ILGWU merger, clippings, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- [Miscellaneous clippings, voting machine diagrams, posters, and scrapbook pages], 1978-1984 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Miscellaneous clippings (Box 5, Folder 1)